Mohayeminul Islam

Email: mohayemin@ualberta.ca • Website: https://mohayemin.github.io

RESEARCH

Research Interest: Library Migration, Software Engineering

Software applications typically depend on libraries that evolve independently of the application. Due to many reasons; e.g., going out of maintenance, or not supporting desired features; application developers may want to replace the existing library with an alternative one, a process known as *Library Migration*. My research goal is to better understand the process and develop tools and techniques for efficient and reliable library migration.

Publications

- A. Jha, M. Islam, and S. Nadi. "JTestMigBench and JTestMigTax: A benchmark and taxonomy for unit test migration". In Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Software Analysis, Evolution and Reengineering (SANER '23), 2023. (Under review)
- S. Ho, V. Majdinasab, M. Islam, D. Costa, E. Shihab, F. Khomh, S. Nadi and M. Raza. "An Empirical Study on Bugs Inside PyTorch". In Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Software Analysis, Evolution and Reengineering (SANER '23), 2023. (Under review)
- M. Islam, T. Toma, M. Selim, A. Gias, and M. Shah. "Design Migration from Procedural to Object-Oriented Paradigm by Clustering Data Call Graph." International Journal of Information Engineering and Electronic Business, vol. 8, no. 2 (2016): 1.
- T. Toma, M. Islam, M. Shoyaib, and S. Islam. "A Dependency Graph Generation Process for Client-side Web Applications." International Journal of Information Engineering and Electronic Business, vol. 7, no. 2 (2015): 38.

Course Projects

- API Migration with Program Synthesis: A Proof of Concept, Winter 2021, Group Project
- An Empirical Study of Parallel Refactorings in Merge Conflicts, Fall 2020, Individual Project
- OO.js: Object-Oriented Design Suggestions for JavaScript Programs, Fall 2020, Individual Project

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Computer Science (in progress)

Started in September 2020

Department of Computing Science, University of Alberta, Canada

Affiliations:

• Sarah Nadi, The Software Maintenance and Reuse Lab

https://sarahnadi.org/smr

• CREATE SE4AI

https://se4ai.org/

Master of Science in Software Engineering

Completed in June 2014

Institute of Information Technology, University of Dhaka, Bangladesh

Affiliation: Shah Khaled, IITDU Optimization group https://sites.google.com/site/iitduoptimization

Bachelor of Information Technology

Completed in December 2012

Institute of Information Technology, University of Dhaka, Bangladesh

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES

- Worked extensively: Python, C#, JavaScript, TypeScript, Java
- Familiar: C, C++, Ruby, Haskell, and a few others

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2+ YEARS

Islamic University of Technology

Assistant Professor

November 2019 - April 2021

Lecturer

September 2018 - October 2019

Courses Taught

- Software Design and Architecture (Summer 2020)
- Design Patterns (Winter 2020)
- Object Oriented Concepts II (Winter 2019, Winter 2020)
- Software Requirements Specification (Summer 2019)

INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

6+ YEARS

Streams Tech Ltd.

• Senior Software Engineer

January 2015 - September 2018

• Software Engineer

March 2013 - December 2014

M&H Informatics (BD) Ltd.

Software Engineer, part-time

March 2012 - February 2013

• Intern Software Engineer

July 2011 - December 2011

Projects

- Time Series GPM process NASA's huge precipitation data to deliver as time series
- SurfGIS a web-based GIS app for viewing, creating, managing, and sharing GIS data

ACTIVITIES AND ACHIEVEMENTS

- Received Alberta Graduate Excellence Scholarship
- Received University of Alberta Doctoral Recruitment Scholarship
- Student Volunteer for International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE 2021)
- Former academic volunteer at Bangladesh Mathematical Olympiad (2008 2011)
- Co-directed Ramanujan Gonit Songho, a local math club in Dhaka (2008 2012)
- Secured first place in an Inter-University Mathematical Olympiad (2009)
- Participated and won prizes at several national-level hackathons in Bangladesh (2011 2015)